<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>古文通止</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>今秘阁</p>
      </publicationStmt>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language>zh-CN</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="image">https://devcn.image.huiyouwenhua.com/image/1696902951102/full/max/0/default.jpg</div>
      <div type="transcript">昔黃帝作内經十八卷靈樞九卷素問九卷迺焉世所奉行唯素問耳越人得其一二而述難經甫謐次而為甲乙諸家之説悉自此始其間或有得失未一可為後世法則謂如南陽活人書稱欬逆者也謹按靈樞經曰新穀氣入于胃與故寒氣相爭故曰噦舉而並之則理可斷矣又如難經弟六十五篇是越人標指靈樞本輸之大畧世或以為流注謹按靈樞經曰所言節者神氣之所遊行出入也非皮肉筋骨也又日神氣者正宗也神氣之所遊行出入者流注也井榮输經合者本輸也舉而並之則知相去是恒品</div>
      <div type="punctuation">昔黃帝作内經十八卷，靈樞九卷，素問九卷，迺其数焉世所奉行，唯素問耳。越人得其一二而述難經，皇甫謐次而為甲乙諸家之説，悉自此始。其間或有得失，未一可為後世法則。謂如南陽活人書稱：「欬逆者也」謹按靈樞經曰：「新穀氣入于胃，與故寒氣相爭，故曰噦。舉而並之則理可斷矣。」又如難經弟六十五篇，是越人標指靈樞本輸之大畧。世或以為流注，謹按靈樞經曰：「所言節者，神氣之所遊行出入也，非皮肉筋骨也。」又日神氣者，正宗也；神氣之所遊行出入者，流注也。井榮输經合者，本輸也。舉而並之則知相去是恒品。</div>
      <div type="note"/>
      <div type="translation_chinese">古时黄帝创作了《内经》十八卷，还有《灵枢》九卷，《素问》九卷。后来这些书被世人所崇奉，唯独《素问》最为普及。越人得到其中的一、二卷后，开始传述难经。皇甫谧次之，形成了甲乙等家的学说，从此开始。在这个过程中，或许有所得有所失，不完全可以成为后世的法则。比如南阳活人写到患者咳嗽、呕吐时说：“欬逆者也”。根据《灵枢经》的记载，新谷物的气进入胃，与旧寒气相冲，因此称之为呕吐。举而并之，就可以明白情况了。再如《难经》有六十五篇，这是越人对《灵枢经》的概括。有人认为这是后人所附加的，但根据《灵枢经》的记载，所说的“节”指的是神气所游走进出的地方，而不是皮肉筋骨。又神气，指正宗。神气所游走进出，就是流注。井荣输经合，是一种记录方法。举而并之，就能知道彼此之间的差距是恒定的。</div>
      <div type="translation_english">In ancient times, Huangdi wrote the Neijing in eighteen volumes, Ling Shu in nine volumes, and Su Wen in nine volumes. These writings became the basis for medical practices followed by subsequent generations, with Su Wen being the most widely recognized. People from Yue later obtained and interpreted difficult texts, followed by Huangfu Mi who further developed various theories and schools of thought, marking the beginning of this tradition. However, there were both successes and shortcomings in these writings, and they cannot be considered definitive guidelines for future generations. For example, the book "Nanyang Huoren" claimed that "coughing is a manifestation of rebellion." This is in contrast to the Ling Shu, which states, "When fresh grain energy enters the stomach and competes with cold energy, it is called cough (hui)." This example illustrates that the findings may differ. Another example is the 65 chapters in the Nie Jing, which were summarized by the people of Yue to be closely related to the Ling Shu. Some people consider this as a later addition, but according to the Ling Shu, it says, "The term 'jie' refers to the movement and entry-exit of spiritual energy, not the skin, flesh, tendons, and bones." Also, the term "shenqi" refers to the authentic teachings, and the movement and entry-exit of spiritual energy is the addition. "Jingrong Shu Jinghe" is the original transmission. When considering these examples collectively, the differences become constant.</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>