<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>古文通止</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>今秘阁</p>
      </publicationStmt>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language>zh-CN</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="image">https://devcn.image.huiyouwenhua.com/image/1696435292994/full/max/0/default.jpg</div>
      <div type="transcript">易傳卷第五李氏集解序卦曰有天地然後有萬物有萬物然後有男女有男女然後有夫婦有夫婦然後有父子有父子然後有君臣有君臣然後有上下有上下然後禮義有所錯韓康伯曰言咸卦之義也成柔上而剛下感應以相與夫婦之象莫美乎斯人倫之道莫大夫婦故夫子殷勤深述其義义崇人倫之</div>
      <div type="punctuation">易傳卷第五
李氏集解

序卦曰：「有天地，然後有萬物；有萬物，然後有男女；有男女，然後有夫婦；有夫婦，然後有父子；有父子，然後有君臣；有君臣，然後有上下；有上下，然後禮義有所錯。」

韓康伯曰：「言咸卦之義也，成柔上而剛下，感應以相與夫婦之象莫美乎斯人倫之道莫大夫婦。故夫子殷勤深述其義，义崇人倫之。」
</div>
      <div type="note">夫子: 夫子指孔子。在古代，“夫子”是用来称呼老师的。
</div>
      <div type="translation_chinese">易经卷第五
李氏的解释

序卦说：“有了天地，才有了万物；有了万物，才有了男女；有了男女，才有了夫妻；有了夫妻，才有了父子；有了父子，才有了君臣；有了君臣，才有了上下；有了上下，才有了礼义的规范。”

韩康伯说：“这是说咸卦的意义，成柔上而刚下，感应而形成夫妻之象，最美的莫过于人伦的道德准则。因此，孔子先生殷勤地详述了它的意义，崇尚人伦之道。”</div>
      <div type="translation_english">Book of Changes, Volume 5
Commentaries by Li Zhi

Introduction to Hexagram:
"There is heaven and earth, and then there are all things. There are all things, and then there are men and women. There are men and women, and then there are husbands and wives. There are husbands and wives, and then there are fathers and sons. There are fathers and sons, and then there are rulers and ministers. There are rulers and ministers, and then there are superiors and inferiors. There are superiors and inferiors, and then there is the presence of ritual and righteousness."

Han Kangbo said, "This speaks of the meaning of the Xian hexagram. The soft is above and the hard is below, resonating and interacting like the images of husband and wife. There is nothing more beautiful than this principle of human relationships, and Confucius diligently elaborated on its meaning, emphasizing the importance of human relationships."

Notes:
"Fu Zi": "Fu Zi" refers to Confucius. In ancient times, "Fu Zi" was used to address teachers.</div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>